Alexey Gronskiy ML Software Engineer / Engineering Manager / TLM

+41798454046 LinkedIn: agronskiy ♂ alexey@gronskiy.com Github: agronskiy ♂ Zurich, Switzerland Homepage: gronskiy.com ♂



Profile

As a mathematician, computer scientist, and engineering leader, I have dedicated my career to the advancement of artificial intelligence through both research and practical application. My experience ranges from developing state-of-the-art machine learning systems for code analysis and aviation safety to leading teams in the full cycle of AI product development.

Areas of experise: ML for automatic vulnerability fixing (Snyk DeepCode AI Fix ②) – Low-memory and low-latency model optimization (quantization, pruning, distillation) – Computer vision for autonomous flight (Daedalean's Spotter ②) – Industrial ML research ("Fixing security vulnerabilities with LLMs", co-author ②) – Data engineering and orchestration – NN verification and certification ("Concepts of design assurance for NNs", co-author ③) – Engineering management, team growth, mentoring.

Experience: 9 years industry (Software Engineering & Management) and 6 years academia (PhD from ETH Zurich, Computer Science)

Skills, Frameworks and Stacks

- Main languages: C++, Python, Go
- Build & CI/CD: Bazel, Pantsbuild, CircleCI, Github Actions
- ML Training: PyTorch, Tensorflow, DeepSpeed;
 Determined AI, Weights & Biases, Vertex AI
- ML Serving: HuggingFace, ONNX, BitsAndBytes/Optimum
- ML Sub-areas: Transformers, U-Nets, ResNets, VAEs; Quantization/Pruning
- Cloud: GCP/AWS, GCS/S3, Firebase
- Data & Formats: PostgreSQL, Redis, MongoDB, Parquet, Kafka
- Deployment & Balancing: k8s, Helm, Terraform, Envoy, Docker
- Observability: Datadog, OpenCensus, Prometheus, Grafana
- Org: Phabricator, JIRA, UML/C4
- DevEx: Git, Mercurial, Bazaar, NeoVim, LATEX

Professional Experience

Engineering manager (ML team) Snyk (snyk.io ♂)

Zurich, Switzerland 06/2023 – present

- Driving the launch of Snyk DeepCode Al Fix of from Beta to GA via a series of steady model improvements and closing the product-train-eval feedback loop.
- Oversaw development of in-house data labelling service and launched labelling collaborations with external parties, improving the automated fix coverage from 1 to 7 programming languages, and increasing the quality by 20%.
- Oversaw transition of ML train/eval and crawling pipelines to automated KubeFlow cloud, speeding up the release and experimentation from days to hours.
- Developed services for hosting company-wide ML hackathons and label-a-thons. Implemented event-streaming service for large scala analytics of DeepCode AI Fix.
- Led and grew a team from 3 to 7 engineers; advised MSc theses (jointly with ETH Zurich).
- Skills & Stacks: C++17/20 (for serving), Python/PyTorch/ONNX (for deep learning stack), Go (for LSP), Bazel, Kafka, k8s (GKE/EKS), Helm, Envoy, Docker; production cycle, requirements management, mentoring, people management.

Senior ML SWE, Tech lead Snyk (snyk.io ♂)

Zurich, Switzerland 04/2021 – 06/2023

- Beta-launched product for automatic vulnerability fixing (Snyk DeepCode AI Fix &), including serving architecture and implementation.
- Created and internally championed the initial PoC of Snyk Code Custom Rules ©.
- Built the infrastructure for training/evaluation and serving of LLMs for code repair and search (real-time inference of 3B+ models).
 Designed and built internal libraries for simplified storage of various artifacts over any S3-compliant storage.
- Brought in codebase best practices, test-driven development, scaled the experimentation.
- Publications: "DeepCode AI Fix: Fixing Security Vulnerabilities with Large Language Models" (arXiv &).
- Skills: C++17/20, Bazel; Python/Pytorch/ONNX; Go; k8s (both GKE/Amazon EKS), Helm, Envoy, Docker; Language Server Protocol; Weights & Biases; program analysis.

Senior data engineer SIX Banking Services (six-group.com ♂)

Zurich, Switzerland 12/2020 – 02/2021

- Founding role in a newly established data science unit. Organized technical stack, code review and other processes.
- Performed analytical support of stakeholder business units, provided analysis and computed KPIs for ongoing projects in payment ecosystems.
- Participated in preparatory work for transition to cloud pipelines.
- Skills: Python, Geospatial analysis, Mircosoft Azure (Data Factory, DataLake, Databricks), JFrog Artifactory, data security and compliance.

Machine learning & computer vision engineer Daedalean AI (ddln.ai ♂)

Zurich, Switzerland 06/2018 – 10/2020

- Prototyped real-time visual air-to-air object detection and tracking system, currently Daedalean's core product (Daedalean's Spotter 2).
- Designed and built and in-house model evaluation framework which allowed to automate the release cycle and ablation experiments.
- Shaped out data acquisition and annotation strategies. Defined evaluation metrics, navigated aviation industry standards on operational performance. Supervised interns/MSc students. Carried out flight tests as a fixed-wing aircraft pilot.
- Publications: (with European Aviation Safety Agency) "Concepts of Design Assurance for Neural Networks" (Published by EASA 2).
- **Skills:** C++14, Python, Tensorflow, Git, object detection and tracking, cloud computing and automation (GCP/KubeFlow/Jenkins), technical ownership, requirements design, product development cycle.

Engineering intern Google, Research & Machine Intelligence

Zurich, Switzerland 05/2017 - 09/2017

- Worked on answer ranking module for active question reformulation project. Developed several deep learning models for answer ranking.
- Blog post: "Open Sourcing Active Question Reformulation with Reinforcement Learning" (Google Al blog post ♂).
- Skills: Python, C++11, Blaze (Bazel), Tensorflow (v1), NLP, experimental design, MapReduce (Flume)

Software engineer ABBYY Software (abbyy.com ♂)

Moscow, Russia 04/2010 - 08/2012

- Worked on a framework (ABBYY Compreno ©) for automated native language understanding and translation. Designed, developed SDK wrappers for language morphology analysis and text classification.
- Skills: C++03, C#, COM/COM+/WinAPI, SVN, interface design, internal libraries, UML.

Freelance C++ developer

Moscow, Russia 2008 – 2011

- Developed a cross-platform (Mac/Linux/Windows) tool for photo management, sold and maintained it with multiple publishing houses (archive GitHub).
- Skills: C++03, Qt 4, MercurialHg, PostgreSQL.

Education

PhD in Computer Science ETH Zurich, Dept. of Computer Sience, ML Group

Zurich, Switzerland 2012 – 2018

- Conducted research in theorectical ML (discrete optimization under uncertainty).
- Launched medical collaborations with University Hospital Zurich.
- Supervised several MSc theses.
- Taught "Introduction to Machine Learning" and "Statistical Learning Theory" courses, created a script for the latter.
- Thesis: "Statistical Mechanics and Information Theory for Approximate Robust Inference" (ETH Dissertation ©)

Specialist in Mathematics Moscow State University, Dept. of Mathematics and Mechanics Moscow, Russia 2006 – 2011

- Specialist (equiv. BSc + MSc) degree in Pure and Applied Mathematics, with Honors.
- Thesis: "On some metrical properties of Boolean functions" (https://gron.sk/msc-thesis c²)

Volunteering

Firefighter, Emergency Medical Technitian Zurich Fire & Rescue Service

Zurich, Switzerland 2014 – 2021

- Regularly trained as an ambulance assistant (EMT).
- Participated in ambulance shifts during public events in the city of Zurich.
- Was a first responder to alarms from large-scale emergencies.

Hobbies and Other

• Privat Pilot Licence

Music (flute & guitar)

Sports (running, cycling, karate)

• Technical blog (gronskiy.com/posts ♂)

Languages

• Russian [Native]

• German [Fluent, C2, Goethe]

• English [Fluent]

• French [Fluent, C1, DALF]